<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A bryef [and] short declaracyon made, wherbye euerye chrysten man maye knowe, what is a sacrament Of what partes a sacramente consysteth and is made, for what intent sacramentes were instituted, and what is the pryncypall effect of sacramentes, [and] finally of the abuse of the sacrament of chrystes body and bloud.</title>
            <author>Tracy, Richard, d. 1569.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13855</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24162</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118530</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853737</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853737</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19132</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13855)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19132)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 148:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A bryef [and] short declaracyon made, wherbye euerye chrysten man maye knowe, what is a sacrament Of what partes a sacramente consysteth and is made, for what intent sacramentes were instituted, and what is the pryncypall effect of sacramentes, [and] finally of the abuse of the sacrament of chrystes body and bloud.</title>
                  <author>Tracy, Richard, d. 1569.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Stoughton dwellynge wythin Ludgate, at the sygne of the Bysshoppes Myter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[Anno. 1548. the. 10. of Nouembre]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Rychard Tracye.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A] B.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sacraments --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19132:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19132:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>A bryef &amp; ſhort declaracyon made, wherbye euer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> chryſten man maye knowe, what is a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. Of what partes a ſacraments conſyſteth and is made, for what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſacramentes were inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and what is the pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cypall effect of ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes, &amp; finally of the abuſe of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of chryſten body and bloud.</p>
            <p>Imprinted At London by Robert Stoughton Dwellynge wythin Ludgate. at the ſygne of the Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19132:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19132:2"/>
            <p>AFter the mynd of Saynte Augu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtyne A Sacrament is a vyſyble ſhappe or ſygne of an inuyſyble grace that is as moch to ſaye a ſacrament is an owtward ſigne whereby God tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowghe hys worde declared in the admy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſtracyon of the ſame teſtyfyeth and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureth our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his fauour &amp; good wil &amp; i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this differth a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other natural ſynnes. For euerye naturall ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne repreſenteth &amp; ſygnyfyeth the thynge whreof it is a ſygne, But it hath no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſe of God, ther vnto annexed. But a Sacrament hath a promiſſe of god ther vnto annexyd. Whych maketh the ſame ſygne and outward ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to be a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. And yf the receyuer of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente beleue not the worde of promyſſe declared to hym before the admynyſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t then he receyueth not any ſpyrytuall grace repreſented a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the ſacrament. Allthough he recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d tymes. Thys ſuffyſeth for the dyſcrecyon of a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and allſo the dyuerſyte of a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente from other naturall ſygnes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19132:3"/>
            <p>The partes wherof a ſacrament conſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and is by theſe folowyng. An owt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vyſyble ſubſtaunce and a promyſſe of God made vnto vs: whych pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and declared vnto vs, makyth the vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to be a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto vs whych heare the promiſſe of god declared the thynge and Spyrytuall grace repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented and offred in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrament is ſuch a Parte of the Sacramente that they only receyue it whych beleue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promyſſe of god declared vnto them. And al ſuch as beleue not the promyſſe of god decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto them in the admynyſtracyon of the ſacramente. Allthough they receyue the ſacrament, yet they receue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce repreſented therein.</p>
            <p>The cauſe wherefore ſacramentes were Inſtytuted, is to declare and ſet fourthe the benyfyttes of god exhybyted a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d done to vs. And to prynte and grafte them yn owre Myndes: And ſo confyrme owre fayth ſo that we maie boldlye reyoyce &amp; ſaye, that chriſte and al chryſtes merytes and deſeruinges beowres.</p>
            <p>The effect of Sacramentes is to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb facs="tcp:19132:3"/> euery conſcyence troubled vexed, &amp; op<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſed wyth the condemnacyon and iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemente of goddes lawe and ſentence, gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen vpon al ſynnes. Alſo to comfort them whyche be greued wyth the ſyght of the multytud and gretnes of theyr Synnes and no leſſe wyth the long cotynuaunce, vſe, and perſeueraunce in the ſame. Such Iudgement and ſentence gyuen agaynſt Synnes, wyth the ſyght of their ſynnes, and of the multytude and greatnes, and the long contynuance therein, deſperacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt nedes enſue, &amp; folowe, vntyll they here this promyſſe of God vnto thys ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t annexed or ſuch other lyke w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> they heryng, reioyce inwardly, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>denes &amp; cofort come to receue the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as an erneſte pledg, of remyſſyon of ſynnes purchaſed by Chriſt onlye, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out theyre deſeruynges bi faith i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the promiſſe they beleue chryſtes body and bloude to be flai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſhed for the remyſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes And thus they eate Chryſtes fleſſhe, and drynk hys bloude, the clargy of engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d be herein to be reformed by cauſe they mayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne errours co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to theſe true pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
<pb facs="tcp:19132:4"/> taught by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> premitiue church &amp; al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed fathers, &amp; auncient doctores,</p>
            <div n="1" type="abuse">
               <head>The fyrſt abuſe.</head>
               <p>Fyrſte where ſaynct Auguſtyne a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d other Auncyent wrytters haue taught that the worde of God in the mynyſtracyon of the vyſyble ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, maketh a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t there of oure clergye admynyſter, the vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble ſubſtance, wythout any declaracyon of any worde of Chryſtes Inſtytutyon, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> is not onely agaynſt the doctrine of the primityue church, but alſo agaynſt Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes fyrſte Practyſſe w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> he vſed whan he fyrſte inſtytuted the Same and myny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtred it vnto hys Appoſtles. It is allſo agaynſt the Appoſtles practyſe, as it ape<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryth by Paule whyche ſaythe. He hath deliuered to them, that which he receyued of the lorde, The lord Ieſus in the ſame nyght that he was betrayed, toke breade, and gyuynge thankes, brake it, and ſayde, take, eate, Thys is my body whych ſhall be betrayed for you, do thys in the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of me. Lykewiſe after he had ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped he toke the cuppe. Sayenge. Thys cuppe is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> newe Teſtament, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my bloud
<pb facs="tcp:19132:4"/> as oft as ye ſhal drink of it, drynk it in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remembraunce of me.</p>
               <p>Thys practyſe of Chryſt and of his dyſcyples ſo longe alſo continued, vſed &amp; freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of god ſhuld haue ben a ſuffycye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t doctryne, to all Chriſtes church ouer and beſydes that, Chryſte in the admyniſtracyon of the Sacramente demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded hys dyſcyples, ſaying, do this in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of me, which word (thys) hath relacyon to the hole maner of doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge and alſo ſpeakyng of Chryſte</p>
               <p>Alſo our clergye ſpeake the woordes of Chryſtes inſtytutyon ſecretely which can not proffytte hym whyche heareth the not and alſo yf that he ſhuld heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of chryſtes inſtitucyon pronoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced in the latin tong as our clergy vſe to ſpeake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it could not ꝓfyt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> herer, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lati<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, for he hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he by hys heryng vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandeth them,<note place="margin">1. Cor. ij.</note> &amp; ſo the vyſyble ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce is not become a ſacramente vnto hym for Paule ſayth, that he whych ſpeaketh in the tong or ſtraunge langage or ſpeach ſpeketh to God and not vnto men for no
<pb facs="tcp:19132:5"/> man heareth hym meanynge therbye no man vnderſtandeth hym / becauſe the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rer knoweth not the ſpeache as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth after, wher Paul ſayth, yf I knowe not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue &amp; meaning of the voyce, I ſhalbe to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> ſpeaketh an alyaunt, &amp; to me he ſhalbe an alyaun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or ſtraunger, fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther he ſayth, Bretheren yf I ſhall come vnto you ſpeakyng in tonges or ſtraung ſpeaches what ſhall I profyt you, except I ſpeake vnto you eyther in reuelacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or knowledg or in propheſy, or in lerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, for he w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> preacheth or prophecyeth, ſpeaketh vnto me, for edyfyeng and confort, he w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> ſpeketh in the tong edyfyeth hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> propheſyeth edyfyeth the church of god. Wherfore Paul comaundeth all thinges to be done accordyng to an ordre, &amp; to the edyfyeng of the Church ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Paul ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had rather ſpeke fyue wordes in his ſence, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might therw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> inſtruct &amp; teach other then x.M. wordes in the tounge, in ſo much as he concludeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if any man ſpeake in a ſtraung tong in the church let hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pray that hys ſpeach may be interpre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and yf there be no interpreter to decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re
<pb facs="tcp:19132:5"/> the meanynge of hys tonge or ſtraung ſpeache then let, hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hold hys peaſe &amp; kepe ſylence in the Church, &amp; ſpeake to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf and to God. By al this chapter meany<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld ſpeake in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſuch to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g or ſpech w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> they kno not nor vndſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take no comodity &amp; proffit thereby. And bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergy ſpeke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes inſtitucyon in latin ſecretly they take awai fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch as vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> latin tong <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; further bycauſe they ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woordes of Chryſtes inſtytucyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo ſecretly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nether latin ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor inglyſh ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do know or vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d what they ſignify or mean therfor the clergy adminiſter no ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, for the wordes of CHRISTS inſtitucyon pronoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced and declared in the admynyſtracyon of the viſykle ſubſtaunce, cauſeth it to be a ſacrament but doubtles the blind errour is ouerflowen the hole Chryſten church for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> punyſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the people for their iniquitie committed agaynſt God, as it a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pereth in Deu. wher God for the ſynne of the people declarethe manye curſes,<note place="margin">deu. xxviij.</note> &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:19132:6"/> malcoyetyons, to come vppon them amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geſt the whych punyſhement is rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that God wyll ſend a myghtye peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from afarre and froward, ſtyfnecked and olde people whoſe voyce the People ſhall not knowe nor vnderſtande what they ſpeake. The ſame punyſſhemente the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phet Ieremye doth propheſye, to come vpon the people.</p>
               <p>Chryſt gaue the Appoſtles the grace of tongues,<note place="margin">Actes. ij.</note> that who ſo euer hearde them, ſpeake, dyd vnderſtand them i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their owne language and Speache by thys gyft it appereth manyfeſtly, that god wold hys people, to be taught in ſuch forme and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dycyones, that they myght perceyue the ſence and vnderſtandynge, of the woord &amp; myſteryes oft ſpoken in a ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge tong which they do not vnderſtand, profyteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not. But bycauſe owre clergye wyll not obey gods commaundemente, which is to preache the goſpell, and to teache the people accordynge to goddes commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t god hathe gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer, to folow theyr wycked thoughtes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> they wolde haue turned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yf they had folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed
<pb facs="tcp:19132:6"/> hys cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel: &amp; declared, &amp; made ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys wordes to the people as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Iohn .viij. and Ieremye .xxiii ſayenge yf they had ſtand in my cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel &amp; taught my people to know my wordes truly I wolde haue turned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from theyre euyll wayes, and from theyr mooſte wycked thoughtes. And bycauſe they haue not fedd the flocke, God threreneth them by hys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>phete Ezechyell, Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng, I wyll requyre my flock vpon the hands of my Shepperdes. I wyll make them craſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhal not fead the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no more, nor ſhal not fead theyr ſelues doutles thys punyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, is come euen vppon owre clergye for ther were neuer ſo many ygnoraunt ſheperdes, whych ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not fead theyr flocke nor excute theyre offyce</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="abuse">
               <head>The ſeconde abuſe</head>
               <p>The Clergy be no leſſe to be reprehendyd and alſo reformed whych receue the hole ſacrament to them ſelues not dyſtrybu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge it to the people, contrary to chriſtes practyſſe whyche at hys laſte ſupper dyd not onely eate and drynk, hym ſelfe, But alſo gaue the ſame vnto all whych were
<pb facs="tcp:19132:7"/> ther preſent, ſygnyfyeng and expreſſyng, therby y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyth all hys merytes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyffytes, ſhulde be common to all hys Electe, &amp; Choſen, &amp; no ſynguler, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culyar, to one a lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e thys churlyſſhe fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of eatyng &amp; Drynkyng, by themſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues, not expectyng &amp; tari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g for theyr ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bours is erneſtly reprouyd by the Appo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtle,<note place="margin">j. Cor. xi.</note> Saying bretheren when you come together, to eate, loke or Expect, &amp; tarye one for the other yf any man be hungrye let hym eate at home.</p>
               <p>Yf ſaynct Ambroſe doctryne be true, as dowtleſſe it is who ſo euer Eateth / and Drynketh ſo Churlyſſhelye (that is to receyue the ſacrament in the church ſo pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uatly doth receyue it vnworthelye,<note place="margin">Ambroſe vpon the .i. Corin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .ii. Chapyter</note> to hys eternall Damnacion, Theſe be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> words of ſaynct Ambroſe, he receyueth vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelye whych Celebrateth, the myſterye Otherwyſe then of the lorde it was dely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uered for he can not be deuoute whyche preſumeth otherwyſe, then it was gyuen of the Author or firſt inſtytutor. Alſo the ſame ſayth Therfore yf you ſo come to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether that euerye man myght eate hys owne theſe ſhuld not be don in the church
<pb facs="tcp:19132:7"/> wher the commynge to gether ſhulde be, bycauſe of vnyte &amp; of the myſtery, &amp; not for dyſſenſyon, or for the belly. Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyus that auncyente wryter whych wrot before Sayncte Ambroſe ſayth ye haue defyled, Trulye thys ſupper,<note place="margin">Athanaſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the i. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cor. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .ij. Chap</note> whych be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng the lordes and commen to all men ye haue made it ſynguler, and probate alſo that auncyente clarke and Byſſhoppe, of Conſtantynople, Chryſoſtome, no leſſe reprouethe this Pryuate and chorlyſſche opynyon Saynge Trulye, theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whyche be the Lordes,<note place="margin">vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſte of the Cor. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xx. vij. homylye</note> they be not of thys ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or of an Other, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to all, it is all one thyngt thys word the Lordes, and the woord commen for yf it be of the Lordes as dowbtles it is, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> oughteſt not to receiue it to thy ſelfe as thine own, but to ſet it forth, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly to al for truly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lords but now y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſufreſt not, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but eateſt it to thy ſelf wherfor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtle did ad euery one <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſumeth to eat his own ſupper. Alſo i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame homylye he ſayth. The lorde for thy Sake, dyd gyue hym ſelf but the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of thine own ſelf doſt not make thi brother ꝑtaker w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they
<pb facs="tcp:19132:8"/> Chryſt comaundeth al hys people, to ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no maſter in earthe, not therby prohybi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſeruaunt and euery inſerycure or meane parſon to call hys ſuperyoure lorde or maſter but Chryſt meaneth by hys prohybytyons that hys electe ſhuld not accept any in earthe concernyng the chryſten relygyon to teache them any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doctryne or lernyng than he hathe taughte them whyche was doubtles ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fycyent for them.</p>
               <p>Wherfore ſaynt Ihon the euangelyſt exhortyng all men to cleaue to chryſtes doctryne and not to followe or regarde any mans doctryne,<note place="margin">i. Iohn .ij.</note> ſayth. Let that (mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge) learnynge abyde in you, whych ye haue herde from the begynnynge, for yf that abyde in you whych you haue hard from the begynnyng? ye ſhall alſo abyde in the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne and in the father, yea chryſte hym ſelfe ſayd yf ye abyde in my worde ye ſhalbe my dyſcyples and you ſhal kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we the truth / and the truth ſhall delyuer you wherfor doutles the forſaki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes doctryne and followyng mens doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne is the onely cauſe of all erroure,<note place="margin">Iohn. viii.</note> as
<pb facs="tcp:19132:8"/> it appereth playnely where God by hys prophet Hyeremye,<note place="margin">Iere. xxiij</note> forbyddeth vs to he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re anye preacher whyche Preacheth not hys word ſaying heare not the wordes of the prophetes, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> prophecy to you &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceue you, they ſpeke the viſions of theyr oune hartes &amp; not of the mouthe of the lorde. I dyd not ſende the Prophetes / &amp; they dydde ronne,<note place="margin">Ierem. ix</note> I ſpake not to them and they dyd prophecye. The ſame is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo reproued by the ſame prophet. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Paule pronounceth them accurſed whych preache any other goſpell,<note place="margin">Gallat. iij</note> than y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whych was preached.</p>
               <p>The Auncyent wryters Latyniſt Tertulyan, faythe it is not lawfull,<note place="margin">Tertllian in hys bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> called pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripcions xcv. leafe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> for vs to Cheryſhe or Fauour anye thynge of oure owne Fre wyll, nor yet to choſe any thyng that any other man ſhall bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in hys owne wyl, we haue the Apoſtles of the Lorde, authores and Examples, whych dyd not choſe any thynge of ther owne Fre wyll that, they wolde brynge in but dyd ſett forthe that doctryne faith fullye to the nacyons whych they had re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyued of Chryſte.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19132:9"/>
               <p>Nowe I truſte euery Chryſten manne maye perceaue, howe oure clergy contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Chryſtes doctryne, and alſo practi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe, haue abuſed thys mooſte bleſſed ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of hys body and bloud, and no leſſe contrary to all the auncyent wryters as it appeareth by ſaynt Sipriane,<note place="margin">Sypryane to Seſyliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note> whyche ſayth yf chryſt ought onely to be hard, we ought not to take hede or regard what a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny man before vs haue, taught to be do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, but what he whych before al is, chryſt fyrſt hath done, nor we ought not to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the cuſtume of men but the truth of God.</p>
               <p>Nowe chryſten Reader pondre and alſo wel remember that CHRIST when he Admyniſtred the Sacramente to hys dyſcyples declared what benefyt &amp; proffit they ſhuld receaue by hys death w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> was remiſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at theyr ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes but our clergy whan they adminyſtre the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the congregatyon eyther ſpeake ſo ſecretlye that no man heareth them or ſpeake in ſuche a ſpeache, that the congre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gacyon vnderſtand them not or, els whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they adminyſtre they ſpeake of theyr o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne
<pb facs="tcp:19132:9"/> and not the wordes of chryſtes inſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tucyon, whych is manyfeſte, contrarye to chryſtes inſtytucyon and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement ſo that euerye man / whych wel conſydereth theyr doi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges / ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe Iudge them, but the naturall ſeade of Antychryſte. alſo where chryſte admynyſtred / he deſtrybuted the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to all his dyſciples, but oure clargy receyue, all the ſacrament in their pryuat Maſſe to them ſelues, and dyſtrybute it vnto none other, contrarye to the practis of Chryſte, and of hys Appoſtles / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d no leſſe contrary to the practyſe &amp; doctrine of the pryuat Church, and the moſt god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly &amp; clarkly ancyent wryters: ſo that I think ther is nether godly nor lerned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> compareth the lernynge vſe and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſſe of Chryſte / and hys Appoſtelles / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lernynge vſe &amp; practyſſe of our clar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy: But that he will Iudge our clargy to be the mooſt hatefull ennemyes, of Chryſte, and all the chryſten Relygyon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="abuse">
               <head>The thyrd abuſe</head>
               <p>Wher I ſayde i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mi third princyple / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> effecte of ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes was to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte al
<pb facs="tcp:19132:10"/> troubled conſcyences whych be oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed wyth the knowledge &amp; remembraun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of the ſentence of Gods lawe pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced, &amp; geuen agaynſt all ſynners, and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the inward remembraunce and conſyde raſyons of the multytude, and greate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of theyr ſynnes, and of the longe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynuaunce in the ſame, ſo that they in re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membrance of thoſe thynges, be vtterlye adacted and dryuen to extreme deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon for remedy wherof Chryſt mooſte mercyfullye and louyngly (as the true byſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhop of our ſoules, which ſuffered al our temptacyons in hys fleſhe,<note place="margin">Hibre. ix.</note> that he kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng them myght haue the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſyon vpon vs dyd inſtytute and ordei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne thys moſt bleſſed ſacrament of hys bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy &amp; bloud in the admynyſtratyon wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he declared and dyuulged to all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauers therof that hys body ſhuld be be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trayed for vs, and his bloud ſhuld be ſhed for the remyſſyon of theyr Synnes, all thys whych he dyd to the adminyſtracy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of thys bleſſed ſacrament he dyd it for cure example comaunding vs that as of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n as we ſhuld do this we ſhuld do it in
<pb facs="tcp:19132:10"/> remembraunce of him. And his Appoſtle commaunded alſo that as often, as we ſhulde receyue thys ſacrament, we ſhuld ſhewe the death of the lorde: To ſhewe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of the lorde, is to declare that we through oure ſynnes, haue deſerued moſt Iuſtly eternall deathe, from the whyche, we be delyuered onelye thoroughe the paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon, bloudſhedynge, and deathe of oure Lorde Ieſu Chryſte, and by none other meanes.</p>
               <p>O what comfort, quyetnes / and ioye is thys to the troubled and vexed conſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, when he conſydreth this ineſtimable Loue, whych god hath ſhewed vnto him in thys moſt paynefull paſſyon, mooſte cruell and ſhamfull death, of hys only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſonne, and owre onlye ſauyoure Ieſu chriſte. The fearfull and myſerable ſynner, can nowe Boldelye wyth greate gladnes, reyoyce, and ſaye, ſeyng that god oure father hath gyuen vnto vs hys on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye begotten ſonne, for oure redempcyon, we then beyng hys enemyes howe can it be poſſyble, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhuld not alſo now geue vs all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges (bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge his fryndes) w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym yea
<pb facs="tcp:19132:11"/> doutles remyſſyon of Synnes, and eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall lyfe. Thys comfort and yoye, is ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken a waye from vs by oure cleargye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whan they admynyſtre the Sacramente, they neuer ſhewe the Death, of the lorde, ſuffred for oure Redempcyon, not onlye hydynge and kepynge, ſecret, thys eſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable Benyfytte, doone for and to vs, by Ieſu Chryſte / but alſo mooſt wyckedly conuerte and tourne, the benefytte of owr redempcion to them ſelues, declaryng the ſacrament offred vppe to God, by them to be a Sacryfyce, whych Worke, for the workes ſake, deſerueth remyſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Sy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and eternall lyfe. yf that doctryne be True then ther is no thanke to be gyuen to Chryſte, but to oure Pryeſtes, whych dayly do make innumerable Sacrifyces, as they ſaye and Thynke, therbye to take a Waye, and remytt Synnes, Although the holye ſcryptures Saye / that chryſte was the onlye ſacryfyce for ſynne which offred vppe vppon the croſſe ones, was a ſuffycyente ſacrifyce, for euer / and the ſacramente duelye Admynyſtred, in the fourme inſtytuted of Chryſte by the olde
<pb facs="tcp:19132:11"/> fathers called a ſacrifice, becauſe it was a memoryall of chryſtes ſacrifyce, &amp; not be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe it is in it ſelf a ſacrifice ether propici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>atory or ſatiſfactorye, but onely called by the name of a ſacryfyce bycauſe it was a memoryall therof to bryng to our reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunce and to prynte therein the ſacryfi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of Chryſte ones parfectlye done and ꝑ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formed for vs for euer: euen ſo the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyent wryters call the ſacrament of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes body and bloud a ſacryfyce to God for twoo cauſes wherof I haue rehear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed the one, that is to ſaye, becauſe it is a memoryall therof if it be duelye admyni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtred accordyng to chryſtes inſtytucyon / An other cauſe is that we that be chriſtes church, and membres be repreſented, and ſygnyfyed in and by the ſacramente, for our bodyes truly mortyfyed from all lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes and concupyſcence be an acceptable ſacrifice to God as it apereth in the .xii. to the romaynes There Paull ſaythe, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren I beſech you by the mercy of god that ye exhybite youre bodyes a lyuelye and holy ſacryfyce acceptable a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d pleaſing to GOD alſo Peter ſaythe. And you
<pb facs="tcp:19132:12"/> as lyuynge ſtones, be buylded a ſpyritual houſe / an holy preſthode, offerenge ſpyry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſacrifyces / acceptable to god, by Ieſu Chryſte alſo ſayncte Auguſtyne, in a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to yonge Chyldren ſayth, yf ye wyll vnderſtande what is the body of Chryſt, heare the Appoſtles ſayinge. Ye be the body of chryſt, membres of membre, yf therefore ye be of the bodye Chryſte, and membres? your myſterye is ſee vpon the boorde, of the lorde / you receyue the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the lord, vnto that you be, ye An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, Amen. And ſo anſwerynge you ſubſcrybe or affyrme, alſo the ſame doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours wrytynge vpon the holye feaſte of Eaſter, ſaythe becauſe Chryſte hath ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffred for vs, he hath commended to vs, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thys ſacramente hys bodye and bloude, whych alſo he hath made vs, our ſelues, for we be made his body, and through his mercy, we be the ſame, whych we receyue</p>
               <p>Thus the holy doctors, in the prymatiue Church, cauled the, ſacramente, a ſacrifice wherin we offer owre ſelues a lyuynge Sacryfyce, from all ſynnes mortyfyed,
<pb facs="tcp:19132:12"/> and deade not meanynge that the pryeſts ſhulde offre a Sacryfyce to GOD for ſynne, whych oblacyons ſhould defyne re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſſyon of Synne, euer for the workes ſake as folyſh Sophyſters wryte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the holy ſcryptures.</p>
               <p>What lyuynge Creatures hearynge Sayncte Auguſtyne wrytting in thys maner of the ſacrament wyl not Iudg it the ſpeache a Myſtycall ſpeache, and not to be taken as the woordes ſounde, Alſo oure clargye offerynge vs the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, geue it to GOD as a Sacryfyce for Synne, whyche we be commaunded of Chryſte to receaue as a memoryall of a benefytte geuen by hym vnto vs, to nou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryſſhe and confyrme oure faythe thereby and not to be geuen by vs vnto hym.</p>
               <p>Thus they declare them ſelues, to be ryghte Antychryſtes whyche many<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſtlye chaunge CHRISTES or: denaunces and vſe them cleane contrary turnyng receauyng, to geuing, thys is not
<pb facs="tcp:19132:13"/> to do theſe thynges, in the remembraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of Chriſt, but rather to put al Chriſtes doynges out of remembraunce.</p>
               <p>They ſell the ſame to vs for moneye whych Chriſt hath geuen vs frely, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore they make vs very fooles, to bye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our money that thynge whych is our ou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne moſt ſurely alreadye, by goddes gyfte And thus by byenge of oure owne, we not only lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe our monye, but alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Simony, byeng the ſpyrytuall gyfte of God for temporall rewarde.</p>
               <p>The clergy alſo robbe not onelye the poore wyddowes but manye other alſo takyng money for the applyenge of a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament as a ſacrifyce, for the dead w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not eate it nor do it in the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of Chryſte nor geue thankes for it which is required of euery faythfull receauer ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, to do. For as the wordes of God pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyteth no man, but only ſuch as hereth it &amp; beleueth it that ſo in lyke maner the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment profyteth not any man except he re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceue it and beleue the promyſes therto an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nexed, thys is the mooſt wycked crafte &amp; ſubtilty of the deuel, that all ſuch thing
<pb facs="tcp:19132:13"/> whych be mooſt Godly, &amp; ſo proffitable to all men that by theyr craft or ſubtilty they can not cauſe ſuch thinges to be had in hatred then ſeke they, out newe pellices &amp; craftes wherby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of ſuch godly thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges way be kept ſecret or els vnknowen or not regarded or els ſo altered &amp; chaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the proffytable effect therof be not perceyued yet whyle they permyt and let the name of the thing continue in a graet admyration and eſtimacyon but not pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fytable to men. And thus oftentymes it is come to paſſe that ſuch thinges w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> we reinſtituted and ordeyned very proffyta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble to men nowe through the vſe (or mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re truly ſayde abuſe) of them, they be bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me very vnpoffytable, hurtfull and alſo wycked.</p>
               <p>The onely cauſe of thys is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe not Chryſte, in doctryne, and exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple but with great gredynes folow the fond opynyon of men, where God by hys pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet reproueth vs ſaying my people ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue done twoo euelles,<note place="margin">Eſaye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> they haue forſaken me the fountayne of lyfe and dygged the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeſternes euen ſuch as can not holde wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters
<pb facs="tcp:19132:14"/> alſo Cypryane that bleſſed Martyr, and auncyent wryter,<note place="margin">Sypryane to Seſyliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note> ſayth, Ieſus chriſt our lord he is the hygh Pryſt, by god the father, and he fyrſte offred Sacryfyce, to god the father, and commaunded that to be done, in the remembraunce of hym. Verelye that pryſte occupyeth trulye the Roume / and ſtede of chryſt whych folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that, whych chryſte dyd, and then offreth a true ſacryfyceful in the church, to god the father: when he Begynnythe, euen ſo to offer, as he ſeeth and parcey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth chryſte to haue offred. But other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe all the Lernyng, of relygyon, and of the trueth is conuerted and ouerthrowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yf that whych is ſpyrytually commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded be not faythfully obſerued and kept. Therfore the cleargye ought to be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, by the kynge and hys honorable cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell, that from Henceforthe, they ſhulde not make any ſacryfyce, for quycke and dead, of the ſacramente whych ſacryfyce, for the workes ſake, ſhulde deſerue remy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion of ſynnes for ther is no thyng more contrarye to remyſſyon of ſynnes / frely gyuen by grace, alſo it is playne contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:19132:14"/> to Chriſtes fyrſt inſtitucyon of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment which ordeyned it to be a memory all of Chryſtes onely ſacryfyce wherin we receaue remyſſyon of Sinnes.</p>
               <p>And yf the pryeſtes ſacramente be a ſacryfyce, for the ſynnes of the quick and of the deade. why than is not the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whych the lay men receyue, as well a ſacryfyce for the quyck and the dead or els let our clergy ſhewe by the ſcrypturs howe theyr ſacrament, is of more value, befor God then ours of the layety? And yet I doubt not but yf a laye man ſhuld dayly receaue the ſacrament and take mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney therfore ſayinge that he dyd make a ſacryfyce for the remiſſyon of the ſynnes of the quyck and the dead that our clergy wold not ſeaſe vntyl they wyth fyer had made hym dead, and not lyuing and quic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke. Thus it is come to pas that the vſe of the ſacrament onely ſerueth the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſe appetyte, Dronkennes, whordome and iuſt of the wycked pryeſts. And not one miniſtre therof, adminiſtre it duely as
<pb facs="tcp:19132:15"/> Chryſte inſtytuted, it that is for the ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytuall comforte, and for the confyrma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of the faythe of the receyuer of the ſacrament becauſe the word of Chriſtes Inſtytucyon, is not declared in the admy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſtracyon of the Sacrament chryſte is not Receyued, whyche onelye by faythe muſte be receyued, thorough the hearynge of hys woorde declared. And becauſe in the admynyſtracyon of the Sacrament, the cleargye doo not declare the woordes of chryſtes Inſtytucyon, whych woordes by Goddes promyſſe of remyſſyon of Synnes, through Chryſtes Bodye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed, and hys bloud ſhedde: The recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of the Sacrament, receyue it wyth out Fayth, to theyre Dampnacyon, for Faythe, commeth by herynge of goddes woorde whyche they here not declared wherfore they can not beleue.</p>
               <p>Note well Chryſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Reader, whether our clargy be not moſt deteſtable ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> take awaye chryſtes woordes of Inſtytucyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of hys body and bloude in the admynyſtracyon there of wherby the materyal ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of bred
<pb facs="tcp:19132:15"/> and wine, ſhuld be made a ſacrament to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> receyuers therof marke well alſo whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they doo not contrarye to Goddes comaundement, adde and put to wordes of theyr oun faynt imagynacyon &amp; ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whych nother chryſte nor hys Apoſtles nor the prymatyue church dyd other prac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſſe or commaunde.</p>
               <p>Thyrdely conſydere gentell reader that oure cleargye do not declare any benyfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of god ſhewed to vs in Ieſu Chryſt nor they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omforte not vs whych be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed wythſynne nor confyrme owre fayth through chryſtes bodye be trayed:</p>
               <p>And hys bloude ſhed for the remyſſyon of oure ſynnes thus depriue they vs both of the ſacrament and of all chryſtes bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytes and of all conſolacyon and yoye w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> we ſhulde receyue therby. ſo that bothe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe porpoſe and effecte, wherfore chryſt inſtytuted thys ſacrament of hys bodye and Bloud, be vtterly obſcured and taken awaye from vs: And yet when we other preache or wryte agaynſt theſe theyr er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, by them practyſſed contrary to the hoſy ſcryptures and all the auncyent doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tours,
<pb facs="tcp:19132:16"/> they call vs ſacramentaryes, and when we deſyre to haue the ryght ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes practyſed by Chryſte and hys a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſtles to be reſtored, vnto hys Churche than they crye a fagot a fyre, for theſe he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retykes. But nowe Chryſten Reader by the authorytyes before alleged, Iudge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> who be both heritikes and ſacramenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes. And thus I commytte the Chryſten Reader to God, who ſende true and faythfull ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtratours of his ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and true preachers of hys woord. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <byline>Compyled by Rychard Tracye</byline>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Anno .1548. the .10. of Nouembre.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19132:16"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
